Preface

This book is the result of endless efforts and contributions of extremely renowned scholars from various inter-disciplinary backgrounds. The idea for this book was conceptualized while teaching a course on media studies and organizing a Seminar at the Department of Sociology at Jamia Millia Islamia, New Delhi, which finally took its shape at CSSS, JNU, New Delhi. My teaching of the course on social theory and supervision of PhD students in the media studies further galvanized me to develop a book on the issue of media and marginals.

I am immensely grateful to two institutions, the Jawaharlal Nehru University and Jamia Millia Islamia; and all my students and colleagues for their immense support. This book is dedicated to my students, and the teachers at the said universities.

The book is prepared for scholars in sociology, media studies, marginal studies, and social sciences, in general. It is a multidisciplinary work on media and marginal studies with the objective of exploring and understanding the issues related to marginals in Indian society, references to medium, message and its meaning. In continuation of the sociological and media studies tradition for understanding marginals, this volume moves beyond the conventional methodological practices.

The book is an outcome of the collective endeavour of all contributors, and enables scholars to understand and explore the question of media and marginals from the macro to the micro level. The introduction provides a background to this book while discussing the question of the marginal. All the chapters have emphasized on the different dimensions and approaches of the medium, message and meaning. It engages with various questions from sexuality to feminism; the Dalit to disability in cinema; minority to agitation and social movement; labour to theatre; and representation to ideological domination. It uncovers the ontological and epistemological questions related to media and marginals. In general, all the chapters in this book present an entwined analysis of the question related to media and marginals.

I am thankful to Prof Biswajit Das, Prof Neshat Quaiser, Dr Vibodh Parthasarathi, and all my colleagues, students, departmental staff and library staff members of the JNU for their constant support.

I would personally like to thank Mr. Ajay Kumar Jain and Mr. Ananya Jain of Manohar Publications and Distributors for publishing this volume. Many thanks to the anonymous readers of the manuscript for their detailed comments, and the entire Manohar team.

Many thanks to my family members for their unwavering support.

11 November 2024

New Delhi

MANOJ KUMAR JENA

Professor of Sociology and Chairperson

Centre for the Study of Social Systems

School of Social Sciences

JNU, New Delhi

CHAPTER 3

Realities of the Marginal Worker as
Reflected in the Medium of Cinema

M.M. REHMAN AND KANTA REHMAN

INTRODUCTION

Cinema has become a very powerful medium to study, examine and reflect our realities of existence. Ever since its appearance in India, the medium has been used to entertain, educate and disseminate information in a dramatic form and in a most effective manner. Dadasaheb Phalke who learned the craft in England, made the first film in 1913, titled Raja Harishchandra. And since then, the medium has been endlessly essaying in dramatic form many aspects of society in the country. In India, the social realities are very complex. The complexity has become very complicated over the centuries/ millennia. The apparent social structure could be examined from two terms of reference among others, rather simplistically. The terms are ‘the advantaged’ and ‘the disadvantaged groups’. Here in this essay, an attempt has been made to study and examine how the literature of cinema has taken the issues regarding the disadvantaged sections of the society in India. Here, the disadvantaged sections of Indian society are termed as marginals, to examine realities as reflected in some motion pictures produced over the decades.

Initially, cinema was a medium of entertainment. But gradually it became a powerful analytical tool for examining and reflecting the conditions of the marginal of the society. The marginal are identified as the ‘Dalits’, the sex workers, the disadvantaged workers like the agricultural labourers, the distressed marginal farmers, the slum dwellers, the street vendors, small artists and many others. The Indian cinematic literature has been studying and examining the conditions of these sections over the decades and the medium is trying to also send messages that the emerging society looks forward to. In this chapter, an attempt is made to see this aspect.

This chapter provides an overview of the cinema industry and examines how some films reflect and narrate the realities of the existence of some marginalized groups in Indian society.

HISTORICAL PERSPECTIVE

It was 132 years ago, i.e., on 7 July 1892, the first film show was arranged by the agents of two French brothers, Louis and Auguste Lumière, at Watson Hotel in Bombay.1 The show was hailed as the marvel of the century. Another landmark was the construction of the first cinema hall in India in Calcutta in 1907. The hall was known as Elphinstone Picture Palace built by J.F. Madan. Cinema was born abroad i.e., in England. The technique of film production was not known to the Indians initially. It was Dadasaheb Phalke who was the first foreign returned cine-technician. Dadasaheb learned the craft of filmmaking from Cecil Hepworth who was the prominent producer at Walton in England, in 1912. However, the turning event took place in 1912. It was in this year that the first film titled Raja Harishchandra was produced by Dadasaheb Phalke. This 3,700 feet length film was released on 3 May 1913, at the coronation cinematography in Bombay (now Mumbai). From then on, Bombay (henceforth Mumbai) nurtured and maintained by a veteran and pioneer like Dadasaheb Phalke, has occupied an important place in the industry. It is the first city where the film was produced and has remained as the dreamland of show business.

Beginning with a handful of people, today the ‘industry’ employs several lakh people. The industry is now spread over several states such as Tamil Nadu, Maharashtra, Andhra Pradesh, West Bengal, Karnataka, Gujarat, Odisha, Kerala, Assam, Manipur, etc.

EARLIER MILIEU

Filmmaking began in India when the country was under the colonial regime. It was also a period when the freedom movement was beginning to peak. The country was witnessing an upsurge of expectations for freedom from the British Empire. The situation was, therefore, quite volatile. The empire was very cautious about allowing people to express their thoughts either through print or audiovisual mediums. Censorship was quite strict. The situation was aptly described by V. Shantaram. He writes:

In the old days, the Censors were more concerned with politics than morality. In 1930, I had to change the title of a film from Swarajya to Uday Kal to satisfy the foreign censors. With the advent of freedom, there was a natural shift towards puritanism. In their zeal to preserve our ancient traditions and culture, the censors became increasingly puritanical and moralistic in their outlook. However, one expected that, with time, the zeal would die away, just as the prejudices against the British have died away’ (Shantaram: 1963).

Shantaram, however, expressed his dismay, that even after the independence, the situation had not improved. He said,

But censors have not been able to keep pace with the changing social conditions and manners. I, for one, would not plead for a license to show anything obscene or vulgar: but, at the same time, I would call upon the censors to be more rational and uniform in judging films (ibid., p. 110).

This indicates that there were and still are obstacles to filming subjects that may not be palatable to the existing power structure, and the reasons may be many. Therefore, subjects to be picturized have to adapt to the rules of the rulers. This is because ideas never die. In a segregated and differentiated socio-economic and political system, the call for justice and equality might be disconcerting to the advantaged groups and their power instrument. This is one side of the medium cinema and its expression from the supply angle. There is another side, i.e., the demand side. On the demand side is the audience. The audience decides which film should be viewed and which one not. And the members of the audience are free in their choice. No one has any control over them. It is their money that helps the film industry to survive. As a result, filmmaking is a risky business; and investment in filmmaking is very huge even for a small film. Hence, the producers and the directors have to keep the choices of the audience in view. This way the suppliers are constrained. They will have to create a situation: you win, I win. However, it is not an easy choice. Mehboob Khan says very clearly while raising many problems of the industry:

Public taste influences the quality of films in as much as the producers, while making a film, is guided by the thought of making a commercially successful film—a film which will appeal to the majority of picturegoers. Most of the patrons of Indian films consist of lower-middle-class people and the labour masses who want song and dance and glamour and thrills and laughter and tears and melodrama, all in one film. And this line of entertainment is an ancient tradition with Indian masses… (Mehboob, 1963).

These are the pulls and pressures from both supply and demand sides that determine the type of stories to be turned into cinemas, because filmmaking is both a risky and costly business. Scores of people, like artists, technicians, directors, and a host of others like dress designers, and hairdressers are involved in making a film. Thus, the failure of a film means a heavy loss to the producers. There also have been moral concerns, i.e., cinema’s influence on the ethos and ethics of society. Cinema has a powerful influence on people. Hence, the topics and storylines are expected, to a great extent, to have ‘special approval’. This has been very clearly expressed by one of India’s former Presidents, Dr Sarvepalli Radhakrishnan. He says:

It is essential for all those connected with film production, whether they are directors, producers or actors and actresses, that they should resolve that they will not use their knowledge, their skill, their imaginative power, their artistic ability for any ends other than justice, freedom, peace and dignity; and they will not merely cater to the ruthless intent of certain individuals, who, in their anxiety to make profits, tend to corrupt human nature, degrade human beings and lower their tastes. That is a danger that we should like to avoid (Radhakrishnan: 1963).

All this has influenced filmmaking—the risks, profits, social situations, political structure and finally people’s expectations. This is brilliantly illustrated by Ingmar Bergman: ‘The creator of the film involved as a means of expression which concerns not only himself but also millions of other people, and more than not he feels the same desire as other artists: ‘I want to succeed today. I want to be a celebrity now. I want to please, to “delight, to move people immediately”’.

Midway between this desire and its realization is found the public, who demands but one thing of the film: ‘I’ve paid, I want to be distracted, swept off my feet, involved; I want to forget my troubles, my family, my work, I want to get away from myself. Here I am, seated in the darkness, and like a woman about to give birth, I want deliverance.’

The filmmaker who is aware of these demands and who lives on the money of the public is placed in a situation which is difficult, and which creates obligations for him (1998) (quoted in Chanana: 1998).

The limitations of expressing through cinema are much more complex than any other medium. The writer of books, articles or stories need not invest so much money in the process of expressing her/his ideas. But cinema producers cannot take unlimited liberty because of money, profit and social and political ‘permission’ both ‘covert and overt’.

Films are a form of literature. It is audiovisual literature that depicts any phenomenon in the most visually accurate manner. It can depict and describe any subject—physical and emotional. As we have noted in the beginning, in India the major focus of filmmaking was stories and ideas available in our written literature. And it was initiated with Raja Harishchandra, by Dadasaheb Phalke, the father of Indian Cinema.

However, after a long time, since the beginning of filmmaking in India, the issues and problems of workers, their workplace relations, organization and struggle began to get attention from some filmmakers both in the mainstream Hindi Cinema and in regional cinemas.

STUDY OF SELECTED HINDI CINEMA

Here an attempt has been made to examine some films produced in the medium of Hindi. The purpose is to see, to what extent, the films narrated the existing conditions and what message they attempted to deliver by the directors and producers and to the audience.

Damul

One of the most exploited segments of workers in India is constituted by the bonded labourers. They existed in the far and long past; they still exist in thousands and they will continue to exist in future as well. In 1968, an act was passed to abolish the bonded labour system. But it has been so pernicious and resilient, that incidences of their exploitation is quite common. To highlight their plight, filmmaker Prakash Jha made the film. It was released in 1985. Helmed by talented actors like Deepti Naval, Annu Kapoor, Manohar Singh and others, the film narrated precarious and exploitative situations in which the bonded system is perpetuated. The important points which emerge from the narrative are that a sectarian social system, skewed distribution of land and uneven participation as owner and owner are responsible for the existence of the system of bonded labour. The bonded labourers, being the most marginalized, do not have much access to any institution for the redressal of their problems. They are unorganized and unregulated. The film narrates the plight and suffering of the bonded labourers in a very touching manner along with unravelling the complexity of socio-economic system. However, the film does not provide any way to escape the system. Intervention by some worker’s organizations would have indicated that an attempt could be made to change the situation. The film describes a situation as it is along with many issues that contribute to the existence of bonded labour in India today.

Paar

The film Paar (Crossing) was made by Gautam Ghosh which depicted the cruel existence of a migrant couple in Calcutta (Kolkata). Helmed by Shabana Azmi and Nasiruddin Shah, the film narrates the difficulties faced by migrant workers who belong to the socio-economically disadvantaged groups in society. And being highly disadvantaged, often, they accept the most difficult, dirty and dangerous/works/jobs (Shabana: 2012). This is amply illustrated in the film. Once again, the film does not show us any sign of redemption. A flicker of hope should have a great idea to be thrown into the narrative.

Coolie

One of the most unprotective groups of workers is constituted by the coolies (porter). They are engaged in carrting luggage of travelers. More often they are treated very badly by people who use their services. The film coolie depicts the realities of the lives of coolies who could be found in many large railway stations in India. The director narrates the living and working conditions of coolies and shows their struggles and achievements. The film finally tries to bring the socio-cultural milieu into perspective. The film starred Amitabh Bachchan, Kader Khan and others. It was directed by Manmohan Desai.

Kaala Patthar

This film was produced and directed by Yash Chopra and released in 1979. The film story is based on the tragic incident of an accident that took place in Chasnala in Dhanbad. Yash Chopra has tried to highlight the sufferings of the workers, engaged in coal mines and makes a point about how management is indifferent to workers’ sufferings. This film starred Amitabh Bachchan and Rakhee.

Naxal

The film was directed and produced by K. Abbas and starred Mithun Chakraborty, Smita Patil and others. Abbas has tried to depict the problems and issues that led to the birth of the Naxalite movement. He highlighted the dynamics of a socio-economic system that was exploitative which led to rebellion. However, the film does not provide us with any trajectory which can help to change the socio-economic system.

Mirch Masala

The film was helmed by Naseeruddin Shah, Smita Patil and others. It was directed by Ketan Mehta. The film picturizes the oppression of poor women and their efforts to organize themselves to protect their honour and dignity. This film gives an idea of women’s organizations and the technique for thwarting harassment by privileged people.

Importance of the medium, films unlike books could be read by anybody, literate and illiterate alike. It is a powerful means to disseminate information, either for simple knowledge or for entertainment and education which includes skills and ideas. Its impacts are immediate, and get internalized by many. It may encourage, may disappoint, may incite, negatively and positively. Thus, a filmmaker is constrained by factors like who are producing a film, either for profit only or for sending a social message. The power of films has been aptly noted by India’s first President Dr Rajendra Prasad: ‘As a medium of education, films have come to be looked upon as a vital factor the world over. In the more advanced countries of the West, films were being used for spreading education. I am sure we too, in India will be making the fullest use of films in educating our people’ (Adarsh: 1963).

During the last several decades, we have witnessed several controversies and conflicts around several films, mostly related to films with historical backgrounds or films with a religious perspective. The controversy around the film Padmavat and earlier around the Naxalite are an example of constraints that the filmmakers have to take into consideration. People’s choices and dignity as social and economic groups have to be respectfully protected.

Workers, especially the marginal segments, are exploited, oppressed and unorganized and sometimes disorganized. To articulate and express their situations through film narrative scientifically, one requires proper terms of reference and contexts. However, this is not an easy task. The most powerful organization in human society is the government/state. It perpetuates more often the dominant power and to maintain its power, it perpetuates the exploitative socio-economic and political systems. This conflict is inherent and unavoidable in the explanation and presentation of an exploitative situation. The state power and its beneficiaries more often than not do like the truth of inequality and injustice to be narrated in films because films may tilt their boats.

Because of these constraints, not many feature films are produced in the country depicting the process of exploitation. Nevertheless, many attempts have been made by documentary filmmakers to narrate the plights and problems of marginal workers in the world in general and India in particular. As we have noted, cinema is powerful literature. Human and environmental situations are continuously narrated in a more visually realistic manner which influences human minds very effectively.

CONCLUSION

From the beginning of the making of films, the subjects of marginal workers were not in focus of the film literature. The initial filmmaking in India revolved around history and mythology. In the second wave, the filmmaking was more focused on social and personal relations and their complexities. Of course, the plot, often, highlighted the romantic nature of human lives and also narrated socio-economic conflicts in a socio-political situation. For example, the film Naya Daur illustrated the conflict between the use of automation and non-automated sources of livelihood. Many mainstream Hindi films also depicted the realities of farmers, agricultural labourers, migrant workers, vendors and others. However, little attempt has been made to picture the process of struggles of the marginal workers, the development of their organization and eventually and their salvation from their poverty. The films dealing with marginal workers portrayed them, i.e., the marginal workers as the victims, victimized by others. But the extent of victimization by their ignorance and efforts of their potential have not been adequately narrated in our films. Maybe this is an area in which films can make their foray.

NOTE

1. The dramatic turn in filmmaking took place in India with an exhibition of some films by two French brothers: Louis Lumière and Auguste Lumière. One of the films which they exhibited was titled: Workers Leaving the Lumière Factory (La Sortie des ouviers de Lusine). ‘On 28 December 1895, the Lumières open the first movie theatre in history, showing several short films to a paying audience’ (Kupsc: 1989).

REFERENCES

Angell, Robert (2009). Getting into Films and Television. Oxford: How to Books Ltd.

Adarsh, B.K. (1963). Film Industry in India. Bombay.

Chanana, Upender (1998). Magic and Mystique of Indian Cinema, Television & Video. Mumbai Federation of Western India Cine Employees.

—— (ed.) (1998). A Living Legend: B.R Chopra—50 Years of Creative Association with Cinema. Mumbai: Indian Film Directors’ Association.

Kupsc, Jarek (1989). The History of Cinema for Beginners. Chennai: Orient Longman.

Mitra, Prabodh (1995). 100 Years of Cinema. Calcutta, Nandan.

Mehboob (1963). ‘Quality of Our Films.’ In Adarsh, B.K., Film Industry in India, Bombay.

Radhakrishnan, S. (1963). ‘Films Should Improve the Taste’. In Adarsh, B.K.

Shantaram, V. (1963). ‘Problems Facing the Film Industry’. In Adarsh, B.K.

CHAPTER 8

Media, Minority Consciousness, Memory
Sikhs and 1984*

SHRUTI DEVGAN

Before the process of alienation was set in motion Sikhs never considered themselves a minority. They took for granted that they were equal citizens in a pluralistic society, with equal rights and equal responsibilities. The fact that they are a small numerical minority, only two per cent of the population, has, literally, been pushed down their throats. If the fact of being a numerical minority automatically carries the corollary of second-class citizenship, can any minority feel it has an equal stake in the country? And once the stake is in doubt, can the commitment to the nation be unconditional and complete? (Harji Malik: 1985, 61-2).

This excerpt represents and encapsulates the widespread Sikh sentiment in the aftermath of the anti-Sikh violence of 1984. On 4 June, the most sacred of all Sikh shrines, the Golden Temple or Darbar Sahib, was seized by the Indian army under state auspices, killing the controversial Sikh leader Jarnail Singh Bhindranwale and his followers along with thousands of innocent Sikh pilgrims. This attack on the Darbar Sahib was followed by Prime Minister Indira Gandhi’s assassination on 31 October by her two Sikh bodyguards. This became the pretext for ruthless massacre of Sikhs in the Indian capital city, New Delhi, and other parts of north India. This violence continued unabated and with state sanction until 4 November 1984 even though in popular imagination it is remembered as a sudden outbreak or ‘riots’. Since then, ‘1984’ has become a certain shorthand, symbolizing the tensions between the community and state as well as state-inflicted civilian atrocities and state abuse in Punjab.

In the excerpt above Harji Malik, a Sikh columnist conveys the collective angst of the community post-1984. Despite strains between the central government and Sikh leadership before the 1980s, the community at large had assumed their taken-for-granted status in India. After the events of 1984, however, and the distorted imagery and language manufactured and disseminated by the mass media all Sikhs became stigmatized as the ‘other’ and suspected ‘terrorists’. The state and state-sponsored media not only created and facilitated conditions for a process of misrepresenting the Sikh community but also neglected the role of the central government in brewing tensions that would prove lethal for Sikhs. As Malik points out, there was no natural association between Sikhs’ numerical minority status and minority consciousness before the events of 1984. After the events of 1984, however, the Sikh community was made to feel they occupied a precarious and unstable place in what had so far been perceived as a relatively secure context.

The consequence of these state-created representations is that Sikh memories of 1984 and the community’s interpretations of 1984 events have not found much space in the Indian ‘public sphere’1 (Habermas: 1989; Calhoun: 1992). The Indian state and mass media either continue to reproduce and perpetuate impoverished and one-sided images of Sikhs that first came into circulation in the 1980s or suppress and neglect these memories. An emergence of minority consciousness (Gupta: 1985) that started unfolding in 1984 continues today, albeit veiled in ‘normalcy’ in popular imagination (see e.g. Kaur: 2013). Official memories of 1984 are deliberately frozen and static and these in turn inform popular memory. Dominant memory in India still considers 1984 as an aberration in which the Sikh community at large was responsible. The invasion of the Darbar Sahib in 1984 is justified as necessary and benevolent for upholding national interest and the systematic massacre of October-November are dismissed as ‘riots’ or spontaneous and ‘serendipitous’ (Ghassem-Fachandi: 2012, 9) outbursts. The complexity of the situation in Punjab and labels created by the state and media have not received critical attention with a few scholarly exceptions (see e.g., Major: 1987; Gupta: 1996). Militant counternarratives gained ground in the immediate aftermath of 1984. The state had vested interests in exaggerating these voices and representing them as purely destructive despite the necessity of understanding the complexity of the situation and motivations behind this movement (see Mahmood: 1996). While dominant memories of 1984 are constructed and monopolized by the Indian state, there is an emerging set of diasporic voices counteracting these hegemonic accounts. A section of diaspora Sikhs are documenting and recording experiences of marginalization that they encountered in 1984 and that continue to inform Sikh identity today. The segment of Sikhs engaged in an active process of recreating memories in public spaces informed by the present is doing ‘memory work’ (Haug: 1987; Kuhn: 1995; Sa’adi and Abu-Lughod: 2007). Diasporic memory work is intergenerational. In addition to first generation Sikh immigrants who are direct migrants from India, their children or second generation with ‘postmemories’ or ‘delayed, indirect, secondary’ (Hirsch: 1997, 13) memories of 1984 are actively engaged in representing and reinterpreting 1984 and Sikh identity. Sikhs are using both their diasporic locations as well as availability of digital media to practice memory work.

I will examine media representations of Sikhs in the 1980s and their impact on Sikh identity. I focus mostly on media depictions of events leading up to 1984 and specifically the attack on the Darbar Sahib and Sikh massacres following Indira Gandhi’s assassination. There is a severe paucity of media accounts from this period, because of the large-scale media censorship that was in effect (Singh: 1984; Major: 1987). It is important to remember that state assaults and media manufactured distortions about civilian Sikhs carried beyond that year, even though an analysis of these texts lies outside the scope of this article (see Kumar: 2008 for an examination of media misreporting of human rights abuses in the aftermath of 1984). While mainstream or legacy media such as print, television and radio were strongly influenced by the state in their depiction of events and imagery about the community, there is a shift underway because of transformations in media of communication. As I noted above the Sikh diaspora is playing a key role in initiating these shifts and using digital media as a tool towards this end.

This chapter will address the following questions: What were some representations that Indian mass media constructed and popularized? How did these texts create a process of Sikh marginalization? Why are these representations being contested most emphatically in the diaspora and what are some components of new narratives that diasporic Sikhs are creating via digital technology? I draw on a combination of methods including content analysis of print media,2 radio and television reports, commentaries from journalists and scholars, narrative analysis of 1984 websites as well as personal interviews with Sikhs in North America, United States and Canada. I am glossing over some minute details in this chapter to provide a critical appraisal of media imagery while highlighting the hitherto neglected Sikh point of view.

Legacy media institutionalized feelings of being a minority among Sikhs by producing hegemonic and unchanging representations and memories of 1984. As an antidote to these dominant texts and memories, digital media with its horizontal and diffuse structure is ushering in a shift in imagery. Even though all representations, memories and narratives are inherently selective and incomplete, digital media is making available tools and spaces to piece together imagery and texts that have been suppressed so far. Memory work in and through digital media is proving important in fracturing dominant memories and representations. Diasporic memory work is laying bare the process by which the Sikh community became subordinate by managing and presenting their own narratives, and consequently restoring ‘symmetry of the communication process’ (Goffman: 1959, 8). In the process of creating counter memories to dominant narratives of 1984, a section of diasporic Sikhs engaged in memory work are both drawing on community values and rejuvenating community identity.

MEDIA, REPRESENTATIONS AND MEMORY

Media is not merely a reflection of reality, but it also creates reality (Tuchman: 1978; Schudson: 2011). Despite the veneer of objectivity and value-neutrality, news reports are ‘narratives’ or ‘stories’ that are socially constructed and distilled through a ‘process of selecting, highlighting, framing, shading, and shaping’ (Schudson: 2011, xiv). Mediated images must therefore be understood not as pristine and verbatim accounts of the social world but as ‘representations’. Representation in turn means the process through which people assign meanings to ‘objects, people, events, in the world’ (Hall: 1997, 61). Representation as a process of meaning making is contingent on questions of power (Foucault: 1980). Who assigns meanings to certain groups and events? Why are only some meanings selected to the neglect of others? These questions are important to understand representations, popular texts and imagery. These questions are also critical to understand memory because ‘journalism … is also the first draft of memory’ (Garde-Hansen: 2011, 5). McLuhan ([1964] 1994) advanced that media are extensions of memory. The need to remember and share is profound and keen but human faculties are limited. These limitations were the impetus to create various media forms and practices. However, memories must also be understood as narratives or partial and incomplete interpretations of past based on present time and place.

According to sociologist Maurice Halbwachs, collective memory is a project necessarily situated in the present. Our memories are a product of our belonging to social groups in certain spatial locations based on the present moment. These memories are in turn a significant component of our shared identity. In a similar vein, Hirsch and Smith define cultural memory as ‘an act in the present by which individuals and groups constitute their identities by recalling a shared past on the basis of common, and therefore often contested norms, conventions, and practices’ (2002, 5).

Media is an important vehicle for the production and dissemination of memory. Even within the broad canopy of media, there is a distinction between mainstream or legacy media and digital media. Legacy media produces news stories vertically by relying on ‘journalistic authority’ (Zelizer: 1992). Legacy media also follow certain routines and norms necessary for ‘professional, legacy news making’ (Ostertag and Ortiz: 2013, 5). On the other hand, digital media is free of reliance on journalistic authority. Digital communication and information generation is more horizontal and diffuse. This is because digital platforms such as online discussion forums, columns and blogs are sites for both production as well as consumption of narratives and ‘prosumption’ (Recuber: 2012). The process by which memories are produced and shared are then qualitatively different in these different kinds of media. While legacy media often create memories top-down, digital media are bringing about a democratization of memory as increasing number of people gain access to media through which to communicate, share and store their memories publicly (Garde-Hansen et al.: 2009, 8-19). This is not to say that digital media is free of bias and immune to issues of surveillance and scrutiny,3 but in comparison to mainstream media, digital media are proving indispensable in doing memory work or a deliberate and public reconstruction of pasts based on present contexts.

1984: An Overview

The attack on the Darbar Sahib and the massacre of Sikhs following Indira Gandhi’s assassination was the culmination of at least a decade of strained politics between the state and Sikhs. Until the partition of the Indian subcontinent in 1947 into Hindu-majority India and Muslim predominant Pakistan, despite some simmering discontentment among Sikhs, they formed an alliance with Hindus against Muslim Pakistan (Gupta: 1996). At the time of the partition, Punjab was split into Indian and Pakistani sides, but Sikhs who had continued to stay in India did not receive separate territories because of their small numbers.

Many of the problems that came to headway in 1984 started with peaceful protests led by the Sikh political party the Akali Dal and centred on the document known as the Anandpur Sahib Resolution. The principal demands in the Anandpur Sahib Resolution included: first, the demand for Chandigarh as the capital of Punjab alone rather than both Punjab and Haryana; second, the demand that the sharing of river water between the adjoining states of Punjab, Haryana and Rajasthan be adjudicated by the Supreme Court; and finally, territorial disputes between Punjab and its adjoining province of Haryana be settled by an independent tribunal. These demands along with the lack of Congress (I) leadership in Punjab made the state uncomfortabl.4 This led to an increase of Congress (I) led state interference in the region’s workings.

The lack of success of non-violent protests for regional autonomy yielded the rise of a charismatic Sikh leader, Jarnail Singh Bhindranwale, of small farmer background and who had acquired great popularity as a preacher. His role in interpreting the document and wreaking violence in Punjab is disputed within the community as well as between Sikh scholars and commentators (see e.g., Nayar and Singh: 1984; Sandhu: n.d.). As tensions kept unfolding tensions between the state and Bhindranwale, the latter shifted to the Darbar Sahib complex in 1983. The state under the leadership of Indira Gandhi repressed Sikh voices carried in the Anandpur Sahib Resolution by declaring President’s Rule in Punjab in the same year, dismissing the elected Punjab government and replacing it with her own staff.

On 4 June 1984, the Indian army occupied the Darbar Sahib under the pretext of ‘flushing out terrorists’ and ‘recovering arms’ under a code name, Operation Bluestar (White Paper on the Punjab Agitation 1984). The army occupation killed at least 493 innocent Sikh pilgrims and Jarnail Singh Bhindranwale and his followers. This is only according to official accounts contained in the Indian state issued White Paper. Civil organizations like Movement against State Repression have estimated the number of dead to be over 10,000. The attack on the Darbar Sahib and other gurudwaras or Sikh temples was followed by targeted violence against Sikhs from the evening of 31 October through 4 November 1984. Prime Minister Indira Gandhi’s two Sikh bodyguards assassinated her on 31 October 1984. In the immediate aftermath of Indira Gandhi’s assassination, violence broke out against Sikhs killing more than 3,000 Sikhs in Delhi and several hundred outside Delhi. This was a systematic targeting of Sikhs and included organized ‘slaughter and rape that accompanied looting, arson and burning’ (Kishwar: 1984, 10). Voters’ lists were used to mark Sikh houses and businesses. Poor Sikhs suffered more than middle- or upper-class Sikhs even though all Sikhs were made targets. The famous and controversial writer Khushwant Singh noted at the time that he felt like a Jew in Nazi Germany (1992, 93). He did get refuge in the Swedish embassy, however, unthinkable for Sikhs who faced the brunt of violence. Public buses and trains were used to transfer paid mobs. Mobs were given money and liquor as remuneration to set Sikhs on fire. Sikh men were dragged out of their houses often by their hair or kes5 and burnt and women were raped (Who are the Guilty? [1984] 2003). In official accounts of the time and in memories continuing today, these events were/are dismissed as ‘riots’ or spontaneous and accidental emotional outbursts of Hindus against Sikhs.

Representations, Minority Consciousness and 1984
Pre-1984

Strains between the Indian state and Sikh community were portrayed and refracted selectively by the Indian mass media including national newspapers like The Times of India, The Hindustan Times, Doordarshan and All India Radio. Media was owned and controlled by the state (see e.g., Ohm: 1999) precluding even an attempt at an accurate depiction of events. Even before the invasion of the Darbar Sahib in June, and Prime Minister Indira Gandhi’s assassination in October 1984, the state started manufacturing feelings of alienation among Sikhs at large.

The central government had started creating an antagonistic climate for Sikhs by using several tactics especially between the years 1980-4. These measures included: (a) denying the Sikh political party, the Akali Dal’s demand for greater regional autonomy contained in the Anandpur Sahib Resolution; (b) portraying the Anandpur Sahib Resolution as a secessionist document; and (c) using the state-controlled mass media as a mouthpiece to circulate their one-sided representations that held Sikhs accountable for the events of 1984.

The Akali Dal and its negotiations with the central government were continually cast in a negative and disruptive light by the state and media. Media reports focused on the threat that Jarnail Singh Bhindranwale’s violent measures posed but did not cover the manipulations of the Congress (I) and its political leadership (see e.g., Nayar and Singh: 1985). The Indian state used the document put forward by the Akali leadership, the Anandpur Sahib Resolution as a tool to further their political ambitions. The three main demands contained in the document (the demand for Chandigarh; river water distribution and river water rights; and deciding territorial disputes by an independent tribunal) were ‘straightforward regional and secular issues’. The very transparency of Akali Dal’s demands and the religious composition of the Akali regional party gave the Congress (I) a reason to ‘communalize’ demands contained in the Anandpur Sahib Resolution and created fear of Sikh separatism among Hindus (Gupta: 1985, 218-9).

The ‘non-reading of the Anandpur Sahib Resolution’ (Gupta: 1985, 221) was deliberate and willfully manipulated for electoral gains. Mass media provided emphatic endorsement and became a carrier for a systematic, sustained and vociferous campaign of ’government misinformation and disinformation on Punjab’ (Gupta: 1985, 221). Harji Malik points out that the overwhelming importance to the separate Sikh state of Khalistan was an invention of the media rather than being representative of majority Sikh sentiment (1985, 39). The anti-Sikh rhetoric contained the message that ‘Sikhs had to be taught a lesson. That “they” had it coming!’ (Malik: 1985, 50). For example, in an article appearing in The Indian Express before the events of 1984, Arun Shourie, who later wrote in support of the Sikh view of the October-November massacre targeted and portrayed the entire Sikh community as greedy, manipulative and anti-national:

A demand born out of whipped-up phobias as the panth6-in-danger, is inherently insatiable. The moment you satisfy a part of the demand, or even all of it, a new and more extreme one is put forth…. Do not lull yourself in the belief that Khalistan is just the brainwave of a Jagjit Singh Chauhan.7 It has an ancestry, and in the eyes of many a respectable one (The Politics of Pandering, 1982).

June 1984

The pattern of partial or non-communication continued during Operation Bluestar. There were huge gaps in the media’s reports of this sinister episode. There was a media blackout during Operation Bluestar and two weeks after the army invasion of the Darbar Sahib, newspapers were not published or were unavailable (Singh: 1984, 1569). The state-controlled television channel, Doordarshan, used language such as ‘fortifications’ inside the Golden Temple and ‘caches of arms’ seized by the army. These images were absorbed passively and unconditionally. Much of this information that media reports on the All India Radio and Doordarshan were conveying was false and exaggerated. Sikhs were successfully labelled destructive ‘terrorists’ while the Indian state and army were applauded for ‘saving’ the country (Malik: 1985, 44). As Pritam Singh writing on the media coverage of Operation Bluestar and what followed notes:

It was obvious that such news manipulation was bound to hurt Sikh sentiments. But consistent with the objectives of the media programmes, what mattered was not the Sikhs susceptibilities but the acceptance of such propaganda material by the wider Hindu population. Consequently, Hindu-Sikh relations were further embittered and communal polarization was sharpened (Singh: 1984, 1571).

Reporter Brahma Chellaney who reported the goings-on inside the Darbar Sahib was harassed and charged with sedition by the government (Ghazali: 1985).

After the invasion of the Darbar Sahib, All India Radio and Doordarshan were assertive in their reporting that ‘no damage has been done to Harmandir Sahib’8 during the army action (Singh: 1984, 1571). This was another glaring omission. Sikhs who visited the complex after the army action and saw the damage firsthand, write of the Harmandir Sahib pockmarked and damaged by bullet marks (Nayar and Singh: 1984). Far from playing an objective role in its coverage of the army invasion, media representations of the events as they unfolded were either absent or heavily partial and one-sided. The media created a climate to fuel feelings of hostility and communalism. The Sikh perspective was left out of mass media reporting systematically and deliberately. A journalist writing in Mainstream magazine legitimized and approved of state actions with complete disregard to the effects of this discourse on the Sikh community:

Could the military action in the Golden Temple have been avoided? If what was happening before the military action had continued for another two or three months, there would have been a massive Hindu backlash. There would have been massacre of Sikhs outside Punjab. The possibility of some sort of coup and the army marching into the Golden Temple…could also not have been ruled out (Kewal Varma, ‘Genesis of Sikh Alienation’, 1984).

Expressing his anger, Patwant Singh, a prominent Sikh writer noted, ‘What to others is just a building is to the Sikhs the supreme symbol of their honor and inspiration’ (1985, 21). State-backed mass media failed deplorably in capturing these community reactions. In an evaluation of media reporting during 1984 and the prolonged period of crisis in which Sikhs were embroiled, independent observers and scholars have noted that leading English national dailies like The Times of India and The Hindustan Times, far from diffusing tensions, caused damage and destruction by inciting communal hatred (Das: 2009).

October-November 1984

The same pattern of partial reporting and/or non-reporting continued in October and November when her Sikh bodyguards assassinated Prime Minister Indira Gandhi. The entire Sikh community was targeted and stigmatized and mass media became the main instrument for forming and communicating these images. The mass media neglected and made invisible the organized massacre of Sikhs and instead fixed attention on the death and funeral of Indira Gandhi (Mitta and Phoolka: 2007). As Assem Shrivastava a witness writes:

Such seemed to have been the depth of state endorsement of the violence. Not one image of the looting and arsoning, let alone of the killing, was ever shown on TV. It would have appeared that the city of 9 or 10 million people was in solemn sorrow and mourning at the death of the great departed leader (‘The Winter in Delhi, 1984’, 2005).

The media designed a narrative of communal ‘rioting’, that was a consequence of Hindus’ inflamed sensibilities. State-controlled radio and television depicted the violence as spontaneous ‘madness’ carried out in ‘grief and anger’ (Who are the Guilty? [1984] 2003, 1). Organized massacre of Sikhs was underplayed as ‘riots’ by the media and this language continues to be used to frame the violence today. The term ‘riots’ evokes spontaneity and suddenness when the attacks on the community were intentional and well planned (Who are the Guilty? [1984] 2003). Doordarshan broadcast images of crowds shouting ‘khoon ka badla khoon say’ (blood for blood). As novelist Jaspreet Singh writes it was later found out that this soundtrack had been created by cabinet ministers and members of parliament (Singh: 2012, 160). The only mention of the brutal mayhem that was unfolding on the streets of Delhi and other parts of North India was depicted in an inadequate and impoverished media summary: ‘There have been some disturbances’. The state controlled All India Radio announced that leaving aside a few episodes ‘the situation was under control’. While international media (Singh: 2012, 160) and therefore diaspora Sikhs were watching qualitatively different images of what was unfolding on the streets of Delhi, Indian viewers saw only Mrs. Gandhi’s body lying in state (Malik: 1985, 50).

The slain Prime Minister’s son, Rajiv Gandhi who succeeded her, justified the violence against Sikhs. Rajiv Gandhi issued a statement on 19 November in which he considered the mass massacre of Sikhs, an emotional reaction or a manifestation of people’s ‘krodh’ or anger and said, jab bada péd girta hai, to dharti hilti hai (when a big tree falls, the earth shakes). The state clearly and neatly abdicated all responsibility.

State narratives made it seem like Sikhs had called on Operation Bluestar and now if a ‘handful’ of Sikhs were killed, it was nothing more than collateral damage. Even though Sikhs in Punjab continue to suffer in the aftermath of state atrocities and media narratives (see Kumar: 2008), mainstream media have been only too eager to integrate ‘former terrorists…within the national imagination as harmless, cheerful tricksters in a slew of Bollywood blockbusters…’ (Kaur: 2013).

COUNTER NARRATIVES

One of the first and few Indian initiated counter narratives to the state came from independent human rights organizations. Writing about the June attacks, the organization Citizens for Democracy included a critique of the official response to the demands in the Anandpur Sahib Resolution. The report entitled ‘Report to the Nation: Oppression in Punjab’ was banned by the Indian government. The report states,

Now in 1984 after the Operation Bluestar suddenly the Government clamped down on Punjab an undeclared emergency. Punjab was cut off from the rest of the country for days, censorship was declared, all Pressmen—both foreign and Indian—were expelled. There was total black-out of news except what was told by the Government-run All Indian Radio and Doordarshan, again bringing back the unpleasant memories of Emergency days…Without a scrap of evidence we were expected to believe that it was Pakistan which was responsible for the growth of terrorism in Punjab and there was a seizure of highly sophisticated weapons (‘Report to the Nation: Oppression in Punjab’: 1985, 5-6).

The active role of the state and state-backed media in starting and fuelling the systematic November massacre has been recorded by civil rights organizations, specifically the People’s Union for Democratic Rights and People’s Union for Civil Liberties (PUDL-PUCL), in their report entitled, ‘Who are the Guilty? Report of a Joint Inquiry into the Causes and Impact of Riots in Delhi from 31 October to 10 November’. The report notes,

The attacks on members of the Sikh community…far from being a spontaneous expression of ‘madness’ and of popular ‘grief and anger’ at Mrs. Gandhi’s assassination as made out to be by the authorities, were the outcome of a well-organized plan marked by acts of deliberate commissions and omissions by important politicians of the Congress (I) at the top and by authorities in the administration (Who are the Guilty? ([1984] 2003, 1).

However, these counter narratives have not led to any major shifts in how 1984 is remembered in the Indian context.

The ascendance of Sikh militancy as resistance to state narratives and state action was the most important set of counter narratives that gained ground in the aftermath of 1984. Once again, as with the events of 1984, the state and media stigmatized and dismissed these voices instead of understanding the issues at stake. The militant movement must be contextualized and understood as more nuanced and complex than state and media portrayals (see Mahmood: 1996). At the same time, however, violent methods that militants subscribed to as a form of resistance drowned voices of suffering and trauma instead of bringing them to the attention of mainstream Indian population. It has also been to the state’s advantage to allow only these dissenting narratives to emerge. The Indian state used militant counter narratives as an instrument to paint Sikhs without qualification as ‘secessionist’ and ‘fundamentalist’ (see Major: 1987 for a discussion of subtle differences between labels).

DIASPORA, DIGITAL MEDIA AND
COUNTER MEMORIES

In opposition to top-down memories created by the state and mass media, a section of diasporic Sikhs are doing memory work by using new digital media. Despite the selectivity of all narratives, these spaces are critical for the community to tell their own version of what they experienced during and since 1984. This memory work emphasizes the ‘grievability’ of all lives (Butler: 2010, 13), not just the lives of majority community members, economically advantaged, or political leaders like Indira Gandhi. ‘Memory workers’ (Stein: 2009) are also using digital media to bring attention to social and economic issues of drug abuse, farmer suicide and female feticide that are rampant in Punjab. Digital spaces are helping Sikh memory workers represent a more complex and differentiated portrait of events than in circulation at present. Some of the websites I analysed include: sikhchic.com (created 2006); ensaaf.org (created 2003), sikhgenocide.org (created 2004); sikhtoons.com (created 2009); sikhmuseum.com (created 2000).

DIGITAL CULTURAL MOMENT

Digital means of communication are new forms of writing, speaking and listening in the cultural moment at which we are located. Digital media is a far more horizontal and diffuse form of information creation and circulation than mainstream media. This horizontality of the digital is especially helpful for suppressed narratives, such as Sikhs’ experiences of 1984. While the Indian mass media has been filtering and obliterating Sikh points of view, digital media with its ease of recording, sharing information and making it public, is ushering in new and engaged ways of communicating with the media. The digital cultural moment is playing a key part in upsetting the dominant narratives on 1984 in circulation and coming up with alternative narratives composed of Sikh voices.

Sikhs are telling their own experiences of 1984 so they can assert acknowledgement and speak about 1984 over non-acknowledgement and silence within and outside the community. Digital technology makes it possible to converge many times, many places, many experiences, many ways of expression- writing, speaking, art, music all at once and this convergence is playing an important part in giving digital memory work on 1984 a distinctive edge. Websites in 1984 contained many kinds of audiovisual texts in addition to written accounts to viscerally evoke readers of texts.

Diaspora, Transnational Connections and
Second Generation

Most memory workers are Sikh women and men9 in the diaspora with direct experiences of 1984 or children of survivors. 1984 is an important component of Sikh identity for this segment and they are taking the initiative to create their own texts of 1984 and share these with the community at large. In the face of physical distance from ‘home’ or Punjab, diasporic Sikhs maintain transnational connections with Punjab. This emotional connection is about nostalgia and a longing for the culture and heritage left behind. But it is also about the emotional connection with loss and suffering that becomes an unbreakable tie. In India speaking about 1984 continues to carry fear of being persecuted and being apprehended as ‘terrorists’ and ‘separatists’. Also, the very shock of what they had witnessed directly or indirectly left the first generation speechless. Immigrant and online contexts are providing ‘safe social spaces’ (personal interview) for writing, talking, sharing and listening about 1984. Loss is both real, that is directly experienced and vicarious or imagined, empathetic suffering felt without direct hurt. Memory work is intergenerationally transmitted.

The second generation’s role is especially important in understanding vicarious or imagined suffering of 1984. They are playing an integral part in carrying out active and activist memory work in 1984 based on their postmemories or delayed and indirect imaginings. As a generation that are ‘digital natives’ (Prensky: 2011) that is they are born into rather than migrate to digital cultures, they are at the forefront in recreating and reconfiguring existing narratives. Further, this generation is simultaneously rooted in Sikhi or the Sikh religious and cultural heritage along with a distance from the Indian state and media memories. As one of my second-generation interviewees explained to me, he felt a deep sense of attachment and affinity with Sikh history and heritage including stories of the Gurus and values of seva or altruistic service and shahidi or martyrdom. Second generation Sikhs admit that they do not take their identity for granted and go about finding a ‘sense of purpose’ because they are questioned about their identity on an everyday basis. Because of this particular cultural and temporal location, second-generation narratives of 1984 are different from state and media accounts. In a personal interview, another of my respondents explained:

… there is very much a strong narrative that’s been painted that is not favorable for Sikhs … in North America, with the benefit of distance you’ve been able to put together a Sikh narrative which is supported by tools of Internet and technology.

Another important trigger for the second generation gravitating towards memory work are the events of 9/11 in the United States specifically. This led the second generation to reflect on their ‘difference’ from the mainstream population in ways they had not done before and go back to tracing their genealogies or start memory work.

Memory work is a two-way process. While diasporic Sikhs are motivated to do memory work because of their direct memories of 1984 or commitment to Sikh values, memory work also helps them strengthen their ties with the community. To this extent, memory work performs the role of rituals (see e.g., Connerton: 1989). Memory workers rejuvenate and revive their belongingness to their group identity by re-presenting their own experiences and imagery. This is especially relevant in diasporic contexts where immigrants must continually reinvent and reconstruct ‘home’ and its memories (Hall: 1980). The struggle with top-imposed representations is a struggle to redefine the past as much as it is a struggle for diasporic Sikhs to keep their community identity dynamic and interactional rather than static and unchanging.

Given the distorted representations of 1984 where all Sikhs are painted as ‘violent’, ‘terrorist’ and responsible for creating 1984, an important theme on all websites is to educate by including testimonies of direct and indirect Sikh accounts. Testimonies are stories told by witnesses of violent and traumatic events to reveal aspects of tragedies that might begin to bring about social change (see for example Wolf: 2007). Testimonies of 1984 are often connected with other important events in Sikh history such as the Jallianwala Bagh Massacre of 1919 in which the British army officer General Dyer ordered the shooting on several innocent Sikhs who had come together for a peaceful protest.

COLONIAL RULE; THE PARTITION OF 1947
AND THE BUILDUP TO OPERATION BLUESTAR

Emotions of anger and disbelief and criticism of the Indian state are part of online accounts. Digital spaces are important platforms to talk back to the dominant memories of 1984. The following account is typical of the way events are traced. The significance of the day of attack is brought out as well as the language clearly expresses the Sikh perspective on Operation Bluestar:

On 4 June 1984, India’s Prime Minister, Indira Gandhi, ordered the Indian Army to invade the Golden Temple Complex in Amritsar, the Sikhs’ national institution. As it was the anniversary of the martyrdom of the Sikhs’ 5th Guru Arjun Dev, it was full of thousands of pilgrims…. On the pretext of apprehending a ‘handful of militants’ lodged inside the Golden Temple, the Indian Army unleashed a terror unprecedented in post-independence India (PS, ensaaf.org).

In addition to creating an educational critique of what transpired during Operation Bluestar and the time that immediately followed, there are several accounts that evoke the sinister atmosphere of the October-November genocide. An instance of evocative memories is feelings of humiliation at letting go of kes or hair and an assault on the Sikh Khalsa body. This is poignantly expressed in accounts such as these:

…Word had spread that Indira Gandhi had been shot dead by her Sikh bodyguards… My father had discarded his turban and worn a helmet to reach home, an act that left a deep wound in his psyche … the next three days were about death… The streets of India’s political capital were littered with burning vehicles, burning houses, burning gurudwaras, burning men. Death was in naked display; turbaned Sikhs easy prey. … (HB, sikhchic. com)

Memory workers are using digital media to fill gaps in representation but also facilitate a movement where this reconfigured imagery can facilitate rehabilitation for survivors of 1984. They want to excavate pasts both to (1) understand Sikh identity in the light of this trauma that repeats itself because of the magnitude of damage; and (2) address present-day problems such as drug abuse and farmer suicides in Punjab that can be traced back to the 1980s and begin creating alternative futures.

Sikhs are also asserting their identity by expressing their alienation with the Indian state and its functionaries—the government, courts, police—and aligning themselves with their places of settlement, without using the language of state-media created labels of ‘extremism’ or ‘fundamentalism’. As one website contributor writes:

I had become a US citizen in the late ‘60s, but when I look back, in my heart I must have maintained a dual identity, and shared my loyalty with India. These strands were finally divided post-1984 … Yet, I continue to acknowledge and treasure the rich culture that shaped me, and immensely value Sikhi that came from that land (IJS, sikhchic.com).

CONCLUSION

State-backed Indian media constructed impoverished and limiting representations of Sikhs in the 1980s, specifically 1984. These media representations are the source of dominant memories of the events. Sikhs’ numerical smallness did not automatically translate into a minority consciousness. Rather, this minority consciousness was manufactured by state actions and mediated texts. Memories of this period continue to impinge on the Sikh identity today but without public space for sharing experiences in the Indian national context. A section of intergenerational diasporic Sikh memory workers are overcoming state-engendered and media circulated fear to create spaces for free and uninhibited discussion of experiences of the time. Digital media is proving indispensable in these efforts. Digital media’s easy accessibility where information is horizontally produced and circulated rather than vertically consumed is a major impetus behind memory work to talk back to dominant memories of 1984. Memory work both builds on belongingness to the Sikh community but also acts as a ritual to rejuvenate community identity and representations.

Memory work around 1984 is emerging and fledgling. While a section of Sikhs in the diaspora are invested in excavating memories and making efforts at placing their narratives alongside official representations, not everyone in the community is an equal participant. The fear of retribution and the solidity of state and mass media accounts continue to haunt the community. The passage of time, however, and the shift toward public commemoration of 1984 in and through digital media is facilitating subtle changes within the community. How will this digital and diasporic memory work affect representations in the mass media and in the Indian national context? Can frozen and static official memories begin to start responding to this memory work? These are questions that time and future research will reveal. In the meantime, the relationship between media, memories and Sikh consciousness alerts us to the durable impact of media texts on producing marginalization.

NOTES

1. Simply put, public sphere can be defined in terms of open access, equal status of participants and rational analysis of alternatives (see also Bernal, 2006).

2. I confine myself to an analysis of English dailies even though print media in India includes regional language publications.

3. See e.g., Jill Lepore. Online: http://www.newyorker.com/reporting/2013/06/24/130624fa_fact_lepore

4. Joyce Pettigrew explains a composite of factors explained the state’s discomfort and insecurities: ‘Three features of Sikh life—that they farmed rich agricultural land, were adjacent to the border, and were prominent in Indian institutions, especially the army—made the process of consolidation of state power in this region essential’ (2006, 90).

5. Unshorn hair is one of the five markers of Khalsa or the dominant form of identity within the community. The five ks: kes or hair, kangha or comb, kirpan or ceremonial dagger, kara or steel bracelet and kachchera or breeches form a sacred composite of Khalsa personhood.

6. Panth means path and means the Sikh community.

7. Jagjit Singh Chauhan was a former state finance minister residing in London and an early advocate of Khalistan.

8. Darbar Sahib.

9. In my interviews, I found that mostly first-generation men are doing memory work in 1984. Among the second generation there is greater gender parity.

REFERENCES

Ahmed, Saifuddin (2010). ‘The Role of the Media during Communal Riots in India: A Study of the 1984 Sikh Riots and the 2002 Gujarat Riots’. Media Asia, 37(2): 103-11.

Bernal, Victoria (2006). ‘Diaspora, Cyberspace and Political Imagination: The Eritrean Diaspora Online’. Global Networks, 6(2): 161-79.

Butler, Judith (2010). Frames of War: When is Life Grievable? London and New York: Verso.

Calhoun, Craig (ed.) (1992). Habermas and the Public Sphere. Cambridge, MA and London: MIT Press.

Citizens for Democracy (1985). ‘Report to the Nation: Oppression in Punjab’. Delhi: Hind Mazdoor Kisan Panchayat.

Connerton, Paul (1989). How Societies Remember. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.

Das, Arjun (2009). ‘Political Crisis and Media’s Role towards Conflict Resolution: A Study in Indian Context’. Presented at Proceedings and e-Journal of the 7th AMSAR Conference on ‘Roles of Media during Political Crisis’ in Bangkok, Thailand.

Eyerman, Ron (2004). ‘Cultural trauma: slavery and the formation of African American identity’. In Jeffrey Alexander et al. (eds.), Cultural Trauma and Collective Identity. Berkeley: University of California Press.

Foucault, Michel (1978). Power/Knowledge: Selected Interviews and Other Writings, 1972-1977. Trans. Alan Sheridan. New York: Pantheon.

Garde-Hansen, Joanne (2011). Media and Memory. Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press.

Garde-Hansen, Joanne, Andrew Hoskins and Anna Reading (eds.) (2009). Save As…Digital Memories. Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan.

Ghassem-Fachandi, Parvis (2012). Pogrom in Gujarat: Hindu Nationalism and anti-Muslim Violence in India. Princeton and Oxford: Princeton University Press.

Ghazali, M. (1985). ‘The Charge is Sedition’, In Patwant Singh and Harji Malik (eds.), Punjab: The Fatal Miscalculation. New Delhi: Crescent.

Goffman, Erving (1959). The Presentation of Self in Everyday Life. New York: Anchor Books

Government of India (1984). White Paper on the Punjab Agitation. New Delhi: Government of India Press

Gupta, Dipankar (1985). ‘The Communalizing of Punjab 1980-1985’. In Patwant Singh and Harji Malik (eds.), Punjab: The Fatal Miscalculation. New Delhi: Crescent.

——. (1996). The Context of Ethnicity: Sikh Identity in a Comparative Perspective. Delhi: Oxford University Press.

Habermas, Jürgen (1989). The Structural Transformation of the Public Sphere. Cambridge: MIT Press.

Halbwachs, Maurice ([1952] 1992). On Collective Memory, ed. and transl. Lewis A. Coser. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.

Hall, Stuart (1997). Representation: Cultural Representations and Signifying Practices. Maidenhead: Open University Press.

——. (1980). ‘Race, Articulation, and Societies Structured in Dominance’. In Sociological Theories: Race and Colonialism. Paris: UNESCO.

Haug, Frigga et al. (eds.) (1987). Female Sexualization: A Collective Work of Memory. London: Verso.

Hirsch, Marianne (1997). Family Frames: Photography, Narrative and Postmemory. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press.

Hirsh, Marianne and Valerie Smith (eds.) (2002). Feminism and Cultural Memory: An Introduction. SIGNS, 28(1): 1-19

Kaur, Ravinder (2013). 1984 and the Spectre of Narendra Modi. Kafila, 1 November 2013. Online: http://kafila.org/2013/11/01/1984-and-the-spectre-of-narendra-modi-ravinder-kaur-sandhu-2/

Kishwar, Madhu (1984). Gangster Rule: The Massacre of the Sikhs. Manushi, 25, 10-32.

Kuhn, Annette (1995). Family Secrets: Acts of Memory and Imagination. London: Verso.

Kumar, Ram Narayan (2008). Terror in Punjab: Narratives, Knowledge and Truth. Delhi: Shipra Publications.

Lepore, Jill. ‘Privacy in an Age of Publicity’. The New Yorker, 24 June 2013. Online: http://www.newyorker.com/reporting/2013/06/24/130624fa_fact_lepore.

Mahmood, Cynthia K. (1996). Fighting for Faith and Nation: Dialogues with Sikh Militants. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press.

Major, Andrew (1987). ‘From Moderates to Secessionists: A Who’s Who of the Punjab Crisis’. Pacific Affairs 60(1): 42-58.

Malik, Harji (1985). ‘The Politics of Alienation’. In Patwant Singh and Harji Malik (eds.), Punjab: The Fatal Miscalculation. New Delhi: Crescent.

McLuhan, Marshall ([1964]1994). Understanding Media: The Extensions of Man. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.

Mitta, Manoj, and H.S. Phoolka (2007). When a Tree Shook Delhi: The 1984 Carnage and its Aftermath. New Delhi: Lotus, Roli Books.

Nayar, Kuldip and Khushwant Singh (1985). Tragedy of Punjab: Operation Bluestar and After. New Delhi: Vision Books.

Ohm, Britta (1999). ‘Doordarshan: Representing the Nation’s State’. In Christiane Brosius and Melissa Butcher (eds.), Image Journeys: Audio-Visual Media and Cultural Change. New Delhi: Sage Publications.

Ostertag, Stephen F. and David G. Ortiz (2013). ‘The Battle Over Meaning: Digitally Mediated Processes of Cultural Trauma and Repair in the Wake of Hurricane Katrina’, American Journal of Cultural Sociology: 1-35.

People’s Union for Democratic Rights and People’s Union for Civil Liberties ([1984] 2003). ‘Who are the Guilty? Report of a Joint Inquiry into the Causes and Impact of Riots in Delhi from 31 October to 10 November’. [online] Available from: http://www.pucl.org/Topics/Religion-communalism/2003/who-are-guilty.htm (accessed in July 2012).

Pettigrew, Joyce (2006). ‘The Indian State, Its Sikh Citizens, and Terror’. In Andrew Strathern, Pamela J. Stewart and Neil L. Whitehead (eds.), Terror and Violence: Imagination and the Unimaginable. London and Ann Arbor, MI: Pluto Press.

Prensky, Marc (2011). ‘Digital Natives, Digital Immigrants’. In Mark Bauerlein (ed.), The Digital Divide. New York: Jeremy P. Tarcher/ Penguin.

Recuber, Timothy (2012). ‘The Prosumption of Commemoration: Disasters, Digital Memory Banks, and Online Collective Memory’. American Behavioral Scientist 56(4): 531-49.

Sa’adi, Ahmad H. and Lila Abu-Lughod (eds.) (2007). Nakba: Palestine, 1948, and the Claims of Memory. New York: Columbia University Press.

Sandhu, Ranbir Singh (n.d.). ‘The Truth Regarding Allegations Against Jarnail Singh Bhindranwale’. Online: http://www.google.com/url?sa=t&rct=j&q=&esrc=s&source=web&cd=1&ved=0CCsQFjAA&url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.sikhgenocide.org%2Fdownloads%2Fsandhu.doc&ei=h6KIUvwJKjjsATkjYHwBg&usg=AFQjCNGQ85gPBtDbHbrQTKD2HZXXQmqglA&sig2=IiM7xs0vtL3hh5OK-Z-aFg&bvm=bv.67720277,d.cWc

Schudson, Michael (2011). The Sociology of News. New York and London: W.W. Norton.

Shourie, Arun. ‘The Politics of Pandering’. The Indian Express, 12 May 1982.

Shrivastava, Aseem. ‘The Winter in Delhi, 1984’. Counterpunch, 10 December 2005.

Singh, Jaspreet (2012). ‘8T4’. Brick, 89: 156-63.

Singh, Khushwant (1992). My Bleeding Punjab. New Delhi: UBSPD.

Singh, Patwant (1985). ‘The Distorting Mirror’. In Patwant Singh and Harji Malik (eds.), Punjab: The Fatal Miscalculation. Delhi: Crescent.

Singh, Pritam (1984). ‘AIR and Doordarshan: Coverage of Punjab after Army Action’. Economic and Political Weekly, 19(36): 1569-71.

Stein, Arlene (2009). ‘Trauma and Origins: Post-Holocaust Genealogists and the Work of Memory’. Qualitative Sociology 32(3): 293-309.

Tuchman, Gaye (1978). Making News: A Study in the Construction of Reality. New York: The Free Press.

Varma, Kewal. ‘Genesis of Sikh Alienation’. Mainstream, 1 September 1984.

Wolf, Diane L. (2007). ‘Holocaust Testimony: Producing Post-Memories, Producing Identities’. In Judith M. Gerson and Diane L. Wolf (eds.), Sociology Confronts the Holocaust: Memories and Identities in Jewish Diasporas. Durham and London: Duke University Press.

Zelizer, Barbie (1992). Covering the Body: The Kennedy Assassination, the Media, and the Shaping of Collective Memory. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.

Electronic Sources

http://www.ensaaf.com (accessed in November 2013).

http://www.sikhchic.com (accessed in November 2013).

http://www.sikhgenocide.org (accessed in November 2013).

http://www.sikhmuseum.com (accessed in November 2013).

http://www.sikhtoons.com (accessed in November 2013).

* This chapter is part of PhD dissertation submitted to Rutgers University, USA.